So back in section nine,
we looked at three of Java's list types.
That was the list interface, the array
list, and also the linked list classes.
Now those form part of the Java
collections framework, and
that framework also includes things
like sets Maps, trees, and ques.
So at the top level of the collections
framework is the collections class.
Now this exposes static methods
that you can operate on collections
such as the sort method that
we've used previously but
they also return collection
objects such as list method.
Now the interfaces in
the collection framework,
what they do is they allow
the framework to be extended.
And they actually define methods for
all the fundamental operations that
really are required for
the various collection types.
Now one of the design goals of
the collections framework was that there
should be good interoperability
amongst various collections, so
not just the ones included
in the framework.
But literally anything that may
also be created in the future
that is a reasonable
representation of a collection.
Now that also includes a raise.
Now a raise themselves couldn't be made
part of the collection framework without
changing the Java language.
However, the framework
does include methods That
enable connections to be move
into arrays and vice versa, and
additionally methods to allow
arrays to be viewed as collections.
So the main components, or
the core elements of the collections
framework are interfaces.
Now these are the abstract,
Types that represent collections,
including this list interface that we've
already seen, as mentioned previously, and
we will be looking at the interface
hierarchy of the collections framework.
Also, included is aggregate operations.
Now, although we've seen
iterate in its earlier videos,
We'll cover them in much more
detail here in this section.
In addition,
another core element is implementations.
Now this is the concrete
implementations of the interface,
including the ArrayList and
Linked List classes.
That's two good examples
of an implementation.
But also, algorithms.
Now the Java JDK provides a range
of polymorphic algorithms
that work on collections objects.
Technically speaking objects that
implement collection interface and
they provide reusable functionality.
So I'll be looking at all these
elements in the section, but I'll do so
by looking at the framework, rather than
producing a video on each element, so
what I'll start with, what I'm gonna
do is review the array list and
link list on objects as well as the list
interface that we've covered previously.
And consider them within the context
of the Collections Framework.
What I will do is use a simple
seatbooking system in theater to see how
these classes that we've used earlier
fit into the Java Collections Framework.
So theater seats will be
numbered with a row letter, and
then a seat number within each row.
I'll keep it simple and not have different
numbers of seats, and that type of thing.
So I'm gonna start off by
creating our theater class.
And that's gonna contain
an inner sync class.
So I'm gonna go over as always,
and come into our package,
right click it, new class, and
we'll call this first one theater.
And we can start by creating a list for
the seats.
So that's what we'll do
first is let the names.
So it's gonna be private
final String theatrename.
Then we're gonna create
a private list of seat objects.
So lists.
Seat of seats, and
seats we're gonna define shortly.
That's gonna be inner class, and
make that a new array list like so.
And incidentally that error on
the first line is gonna go away
once we initialize it, and
if you are Paying attention and
watching the previous section where
I talked about final and so forth.
You'll understand why that error's coming
up and that it'll be fixed once we update
our constructor and we cut into this area
here, most likely because this is weird.
I think it's a bug in IntelliJ.
For some reason, even though
I've selected project structure,
project language level eight, in my
default settings, it's set it to six.
So I'll go back and change it to eight.
The error should go away.
Obviously, we still need to define that
in a class, which we'll do shortly.
So moving on, let's create a constructor,
and the constructor is going
to consist of theater.
Once I do that, that should fix the other
area you can see that area is gone away
now because we have
initialized that object and
we're going to have
a couple of parameters.
Let's also have the number of rows in this
theater int numRows and int seatsPerRow.
And then what we're going to do is,
we're going to allocate.
As I mentioned there’s going to be a seat
number, consists of a row letter and
a sear number.
Theatre seats will be numbered with a row
letter and a seat number, I should say.
So first of all, we're going to create
the last row and do Ent LastRow =
A plus num rows type one.
Then what we're going to do is
cycle through and create a seat for
each one of these theater seats.
So that will be four job row equals A.
A row is less or equal to last row,
row plus plus, so going through all
the rows from A to Z effectively.
Okay, then for each,
we've got the row, and for each row,
we now need to go through and
allocate the seats for that section, so
we need to put 4 int Seat num
standing on one, because obviously we
can't have a seat to starting with zero.
The seat num is to be less than or equal
to seats per row which gave us pass to
the constructor and seat num plus plus
to increment through seat in the row.
Then we're going to create seat object.
Flow plus string formats row,
the row that we've defined,
that we're currently
processing plus string.format.
That's going to be percent O2D,
see now I'm just formatting it so
it looks correct.
And then we're going to add it to our
array list that we've defined on line ten.
So it's seats.addseat.
There's a basic instructor, so
you can see that's created now.
And before we fix this seat error
we'll just create a few other things.
What we'll do is first create a getter for
our theater name.
I'm just adding the getter there and
actually I'll move that.
Below the constructor's probably
a better spot for that.
Clean the code up a bit and put it there.
And the next one we want,
what we'll do is we'll create a few more.
We'll create a reserve seat.
Where it does just as you think it would.
It reserves a particular seat for
our theater.
And we'll also add a get seat where we can
return, or print out the list of seats.
And we'll do the reserve seat first.
That's gonna be public.
Boolean reserve seat string seat number.
And we'll start off with seat,
requested seat is equally to null.
[SOUND]
For Seat and seats.
And we go through all the seats and
were going to do a test to see whether
we can find our particular one,
seat.getseatnumber Number.equals
seat number requested
seat equals seat.
Then we'll break out of it,
cuz we've found the seat.
Then S out of that loop, we're going to
put if Requested seat is equal to null.
And I'll put there is no seat,
seat num in case has been
an invalid seat sentence method.
It returns false in that situation
Because there's no other processing we
can do because we've got an invalid seat.
Otherwise what we're going to
do is return, requested seat,
seat.reserve, and again,
we haven't written the seat class yet,
and that will all be reviewed once we
get to that, so that's how you go about
reserving a seat, and then the last
method, we're going to, or the next method
we're going to create is the get seats,
which is just really for testing purposes.
And it's going to be
public void get seats.
And we're just going to
go four seat seat seats.
And print them out.
So I'll do Seat.getseatnumber Like so.
Okay, so that's the basic code for
the theater.
What we're doing now is
we'll add our private class
which has got some of
these other functions and
will fix up a lot of these errors
that are showing on the screen.
So we're going to go ahead and
do that, so private class seat,
And it's going to have
A private final stream.
Seat number.
We'll get an error until
we initialize that.
Private [INAUDIBLE] reserved.
It was false so I'm gonna save in one to
indicate whether this particular seat
has been reserved or not.
So we'll do our constructor now, and we're
just going to get the seat numbers past
this method, and you'll see when we've
set that and fixed the area that
was showing on long 53, and that's
all our constructor needs to do, and
next we need to fix up some of these,
requested C should be, requested C.
So we need to basically
import this error and
probably the easiest way of doing that
would be to just that fixes that.
We could have done a and
just imported like that fixes that and
some other things.
Just typos but method and
the method that still need to be written.
In a class.
I'll do that.
First, we'll do the reserve.
So I'll go public, boolean reserve.
and the cover,
it will be if not [INAUDIBLE]
.reserve equals true.
So obviously, if it's already reserved,
we're not going to retry and
process it And if that's the case
we were able to reserve it.
We just kinda put a message to the effect
seat + seat number + reserved.
It returned true,
our job is done in that case.
To get started here that's what we'll
do is we'll put an else in here.
We'll put else.
Turn false, because obviously there was
a problem reserving it because it was
already reserved.
You also want to cancel function.
We haven't used that code yet, but
we'll want that, so public Berlin cancel.
And it does things the other way around.
It goes if stop reserve.
Somebody tries to cancel.
If the seat
number has already been reserved well
this particular seat has been reserved.
So if stop reserved and
we put if stop reserve.
Is equal to false.
And reserve it freed up so
I can be allocated again.
"Reservation of seat " +
seatNumber + " cancelled".
Turn true because we
successfully canceled those.
Return false.
We weren't able to cancel because
the seat wasn't was already reserved.
And the last one to fix up
is this get seat number.
Which is just a getter.
So I'm just gonna do getter for
the seat number.
It should fix that and that should
be all the errors that are now fixed
in this class in our first theater class
with the inner class of being seat.
Again just as a recap
looking back up here.
At the top.
The constructor takes a theater name
together with the number of rows and
the number of seats per row.
And it uses these to create
seats which it currently stores
as you can see in the array list on
line 10 which is the seats fueled.
And you can see that I have defined
a couple of other methods as well that
reserve seat.
And also we've created
an inner class receipt and
got the ability to reserve or
cancel A particular seat.
So let's go ahead now and
create the main method.
And that's just gonna create a new theater
and then attempt to reserve the same
seat twice just to confirm
that things are working.
So we'll go back to our menu and here
we're going to create a new reference.
So that's gonna be theater.
Equals new theater.
We'll call it the Olympian.
And again, the parameters here,
just to go back to confirm those,
the parameters we're looking for
here is the number of rows in available
in the theater and the sets per row.
So we're going to start with eight,
so eight rows, with 12 seats per row.
And we'll do a theater.getseats.
We'll call that method just to print
it out, see that it's working.
So let's try running that first.
And you can see that we've got our very
seats there, starting from row A to 0,
1 to 0, 12 and we use that Formatting
class, which I mentioned here,
String.format, to make sure they're all
allocated with a leading 0 if necessary,
and we're going from row A to row H.
Of course that's a total of eight rows.
So that part's working okay,
which is good.
Let's go back to our main.
So let's now try doing a reservation.
So we've got something like,
if(theatre.reserveSeat()) H11.
Please pay.
Seats been reserved.
Else sorry, seat is taken.
So first time you run this,
it should work.
We run this, seat H11 reserve.
So you can see that's working fine.
There's an extra space there.
I should actually probably
look at fixing that.
I must have added two spaces there,
so I'll fix that.
And go back and
run it again just to confirm.
Okay Seat H11 reserved.
Now if we do try and
do the same thing again if I just copy and
paste the same code we should
get an error the second time.
Because of course a previous call to
it should have reserved the seat so
let's just try running that.
Sorry, seat is taken.
So the first time it reserved it and
the second time you can
see that the seat's taken.
So that's good.
That's working fine.
And the other thing we'll do now
is we'll comment out line seven.
Because we can confirm that
the code's working all right, and
the seats are being created correctly.
So I'll comment that out.
So I'm gonna pause the video now and
in the next video we'll continue on and
we're going to look at
changing our data structure,
which is defined in heatre.java on line
ten, the seats using the ArrayList.
We're gonna start changing that to
a few different formats, a list and
then also looking at turning it into
a collection or making it more generic and
seeing how that all works.
So see you in that next video.